Guide to the Sudan Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sudan collection
1885-1997
MS 1543
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.02
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of printed material and photographs relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Sudan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator; transferred from Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1996.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the first accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed material and photographs relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Sudan.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Sudan -- Antiquities; Sudan -- Economic conditions; Sudan -- History -- 1881-1899; Sudan -- Politics and government; Sudan -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Sudan; Gordon Relief Expedition ( 1884-1885)
- Inventory
  - On Patrol in the Sudan, by unidentified soldier in the Egyptian army, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "In the Dongotona mountains," The Forbidden Land: Southern Sudan: an account of genocide, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Gezira Scheme: informational booklets on the development of this area, 1885-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anya Nya, Africans for Ending Genocide in Sudan (AEGIS): newspapers, letters, statements, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Nimeiry, H. E. Gaafar Mohamed?], president of the Democratic Republic of the Sudan, chairman of the Sudanese Socialist Union (SSU): addresses, speeches, programs, 1974, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Regional Assembly of the Southern Region: Proceedings of the Fifth Session, 1975 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [al-Jami'ah; majallah thagafiyah yusdiruha Ittihad Tullab Jami'at al-khurtum?], The University Student's Union, University of Kharktoum, 1978 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Management Development and Productivity Centre: journal, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Regional Ministry of Culture and Information, Southern Region of Sudan: magazines, reports, 1978-1980, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF): military communiqués, press releases, reports, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Muortat-Mayen, G., chairman of Anyanya Patriotic Front (A.P.F.), "The South Sudan Question: The Root Causes", 1984 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Amnesty International: newsletters, bulletins, 1985, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Foreign newspaper clippings, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sudan People's Liberation Movement (SPLM): printed materials, news bulletins, 1985, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: newsletters, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Middle East Studies Association of North America (MESA): letters to General Omar Hassan Al-Bashir, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Research and Communications International, Ltd.;The Sudan Monitor, 0 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sudan Democratic Gazette: a Newsletter for Democratic Pluralism, 0 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Newspapers, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - National Council for Development Projects; Fourth Annual Meeting for Coordination of Work Plans, 1993 November 8-10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Educational/academic journals, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Rahad Irrigation Project: brochures, maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sudan National Population Committee (SNPC): bulletins, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fonds Archinard: inventory reports; Parts 1-11, volumes 5147-5601, undated (Box 2, Folder 24 - 34)
  - Fonds Archinard: inventory reports; Parts 12-25, volumes 5602-5749, 6095-6112, 6135, 6638, 6651, 6851, undated (Box 3, Folder 35 - 48)
  - Sennar Dam Opening Ceremony: photograph album with accompanying printed material pertaining to Lord George Ambrose Lloyd, High Commissioner for the Sudan, 1926 January 21 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - "The Fung Province, Sudan": photograph album, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - The Nyima Jebels, Nuba Mountains Province: military sketch map, 1917 (Folder 5)
  - Copy of the Mahdi's letter to Emin Pasha demanding his surrender, undated (Folder 5)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-201
  - Beny, Ambrose, "Genocide and Slavery in the Sudan: The African and International Response", 1995 November 3-6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interhemispheric Resource Center (IRC) and Institute for Policy Studies, "Foreign Policy in Focus, Sudan," vol. 2, no. 41, 1997 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - McGonagall, William, poem "General Gordon, The Hero of Khartoum", 1885 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Peace and Development Foundation Act, 1991 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Secretariat for Legal Affairs, "Laws of the New Sudan, The Sudan People's Liberation Army (SPLA) Act", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Slatin, Baron Rudolf Carl, letter concerning the rescue of Neufeld [Charles?], 1890 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Sudan, A Newsletter Committed to the Rights and Liberties of African Sudanese People," vol. IV, no. 4, 1994-1995 Winter (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sudan Excavation Committee, banquet programs in honor of explorations of Ancient Mero, 1913 July 22, 1994 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Wells of Abu Klea, or Who Killed John Bull?", 1885 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kidd, K. S. [service reports of a district commissioner among Nilotic tribes near White Nile, Anglo-Egyptian Sudan], 1927-1929 (Folder 2)
- Additional material, 1963-2011; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1963-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, 2000s (Folder 2)